# Gerardo Cortés

I'm a Full-Stack Engineer that has experience leading projects since its architectural conception to its deployment to production. Prone to analyze code metrics and provide an observability solution to increase performance on development time and achieve reliable monitoring while on production.

Residencial Rambla Real, San Rafael, Alajuela, Alajuela. **+506 8844-5022** 

gerardo.cortes.o@gmail.com

cortes-gerardo.com

linkedin.com/in/cortes-gerardo github.com/cortes-gerardo

#### **EXPERIENCE**

### IBM, Heredia— Application Engineer

Jun 2020 - Present

- Develop design, implement, and test application software
- Independently performs analysis to develop and implement high level designs
- Research, develop and propose new technologies to improve application architecture

### Backcountry.com, Lindora— Full-Stack Software Engineer

Jun 2014 - Apr 2020

#### Marketing and Merchandising Team

- Leading a six-member team, on the implementation of a new email service provider for the main sites through a centralized system, applying a stack-based state machine to ensure email delivery.
- Coordination between teams for migration into an ERP (NetSuite), particularly, strategizing execution, and risk assessment to ensure backward compatibility with the inhouse merchandise architecture.
- Ensuring the quality of services provided by standardizing logging, monitoring and alerting, and creation of a load testing template.

#### **Content Team**

- Maintenance and development of projects for teams of creation of content.
- Creation of a tool for non-technical writers to publish HTTP content on the site (Backcountry.com/explore).
- Design and implement an interdepartmental plan to allow backorders limited by the purchase orders.

### Core Commerce Team

● Maintenance, development, and improvement through PCI Compliance, the cart, checkout, and log-in pages.

#### **SKILLS**

Java · Spring Framework ·
Apache Tomcat · Scala · Play
Framework · Maven · Gradle ·
sbt · Python · PostgreSQL ·
MongoDB · RabbitMQ ·
Javascript · NodeJS · Angular2 ·
Docker · Kubernetes · Jenkins ·
HTML · CSS · SASS

#### **CERTIFICATIONS**

Python for Scientists, CeNAT.

Making Sense of Data, Google.

CCNA (CISCO), Instituto Tecnológico de Costa Rica.

Journalistic writing principles for Web, CONARE

Adobe Photoshop, CONARE.

Adobe Indesign, CONARE.

#### **LANGUAGES**

Spanish: native language.

English: advance.

Japanese: beginner.

- Development of the mini-cart on the site.
- Supporting Marketing projects by the implementation of A/B testing, pixel creation, monitoring, alerting, and load testing.

# **Descontadora Nacional S.A.**, Curridabat — Technical Project Manager

MAR 2011 - MAY 2014

- Gathering requirements from the business and negotiation with stakeholders
- Coaching of Java and design patterns to a Jr Developer
- Leading the development of mobile apps using GWT (Google Web Toolkit), Guice, Guava libraries, and Gson.

### **FUNDEVI**, San Pedro — *Software Developer*

MAR 2010 - DEC 2010

- Development of modules in Java and ICE faces for a Web portal.
- Implementation of Invoicing software in PHP and Smarty with MySQL as DB.

# **Vicerrectoría de Acción Social. UCR.,** San Pedro — *Software Developer*

AUG 2007 - FEB 2010

- Development of an Accountant Web platform using ASP.NET.
- Analysis and creation of reports SQL Server Reporting Services and Crystal Reports.
- Implementation, design, and support of the Liferay web portal using HTML / CSS pages.

#### **EDUCATION**

## **Udacity**—Full Stack Web Developer

2020

Syllabus:

- SQL and Data Modeling for the Web
- API Development and Documentation
- Identity Access Management
- Server Deployment and Containerization

#### **Certificate**

### Udacity—Data Structures & Algorithms

2020

Syllabus:

- Data Structures
- Basic Algorithms
- Advanced Algorithms

#### Certificate

### UCR, San Pedro — Computer Science

2006

School of Computer Science and Informatics.

# **Colegio Técnico Don Bosco**, San Bosco — Bachelor of Technology (B.Tech.)

1999 - 2004

#### **RECOMMENDATIONS**

# **Jose Esquivel** — Principal Software Engineer at Backcountry.com

I worked with Gerardo on several different projects at Backcountry, his skills to deliver high-quality software allowed us to put into production solutions that in other occasions would have been impactful to the business and our customers, he thinks in stability, performance, security, and incremental rollouts. He was able to do so by technically leading the ERP go-live for the Company in regards to Product Data and Purchase orders, these integrations had zero impact on the overall put into production. Additionally, Gerardo led the design and architecture of a new Email Service Provider for the company, he engaged with stakeholders, worked on yet another seamless deployment and was the go-to person for both stakeholders and engineers, he is a person that rapidly engages and understands the technical and functional needs, he builds software that delivers value as soon as possible and then iterates on it to guarantee the quality is there for the long term, running chaos testing, load testing and always looking for design and stability patterns to be present.

# **Meghan Erickson** — Engineering Team Lead at Backcountry.com

Gerardo and I worked together in the Marketing, Merchandise & Content Software Team from November 2016 until April 2020. In that time Gerardo emerged into a strong leader who greatly influenced the improved quality of our code and processes. This was illustrated by his constructive feedback in code reviews, his mentorship of newer team members, and his self-started project to standardize logging, metrics, and dashboards across a number of our systems. His project, dubbed 'Logging & Monitoring' was critical for our team during high-demand times (such as Black Friday) and enabled us to quickly identify and resolve issues before such impacts became devastating.

In addition to his technical capabilities, I must highlight Gerardo's exceptional character and reliability. He was a teammate that could always be counted on, evident by the many long, stressful nights and projects and war rooms in which he participated. He was always in the trenches, ready to jump into the fire, not just because he felt responsible

for the systems but also because he felt responsible for the health and morale of his team.

### **Jorge Garita** — Engineering Team Lead at Backcountry.com

I worked with Gerardo for more than 3 years at Backcountry.com. During that period, I saw him grow as a professional who is constantly striving for the highest quality in everything he does. Gerardo is a proficient Software Developer, expert in Java, Javascript and other full-stack technologies. He has SME-level knowledge in Enterprise Architecture and Agile methodologies. He is also a great team player who can always be trusted. Not only will he do what is needed to get things done but he will take as much time as needed to mentor and guide his peers when he is asked for help. Even when that might mean staying after hours or having to catch up later. Gerardo was always focused on customer satisfaction and lead our team towards building a high-performance culture where everyone could be themselves while focusing on being productive. Gerardo possesses a combination of solid tech skills and great leadership and people skills. He pays a lot of attention to detail, provides excellent technical reviews on software designs and implementation, always evaluates the non-functional aspects of software solutions and constantly pushes their peers to do better. He is a great guy and I can say that I thoroughly appreciated working with him at Backcountry and would be happy to work with him again in the future

# **José de Jesus Ulate** — Sr. Software Engineering at Backcountry.com

Me permito informarle que conozco ampliamente al señor Gerardo Cortes Oquendo, cédula de identidad 112490592, y puedo asegurar que es una persona íntegra, estable, responsable y competente. He trabajado con el durante los últimos tres años en el grupo de Mercancías y Mercadeo del departamento de Ingeniería de Backcountry SRL; y puedo dar fe de su trabajo. Él ha participado en proyectos de Desarrollo de Software, actualización y migración de plataformas informáticas; llevándolos desde su planeamiento hasta a un buen término. El es un profesional enfocado en la calidad del trabajo que realiza, siempre vigilante que las tareas asignadas a él se completen de la mejor manera y buscando la mejora continua de los procesos de negocio.

Por lo anterior, no tengo inconveniente alguno en recomendarlo agradeciendo de antemano la atención y facilidades que le pueda brindar. Se extiende la presente para los efectos correspondiente que al interesado convenga.